<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="http://localhost:8081/schemas/elife/article/body.rng"?>

<body xmlns="http://libero.pub" xmlns:elife="http://elifesciences.org" xmlns:iiif="http://libero.pub/iiif" xml:lang="en">
    <p>Blogpost by Naomi Penfold, Innovation Officer</p>
    <p>Today, <a
            href="https://elifesciences.org/for-the-press/e6038800/elife-supports-development-of-open-technology-stack-for-publishing-reproducible-manuscripts-online"
    >we announced a new project collaboration</a> between <a href="http://substance.io/"
    >Substance</a>, <a href="https://stenci.la/">Stencila</a> and eLife, to support the
        development of an open technology stack that will enable researchers to publish reproducible
        manuscripts through online journals. In this blogpost, we outline the background and remit
        of this project. We welcome feedback and contributions: please comment publicly on the
        article using <a href="https://hypothes.is">Hypothes.is</a> or email <a
                href="mailto:innovation@elifesciences.org">innovation@elifesciences.org</a>.</p>
    <section>
        <title>Building on the traditional research article</title>
        <content>
            <p>The research article: a concise narrative describing the background, methods, results
                and interpretation of a body of research work. And while the established format of
                research articles generally allows researchers to describe their work in sufficient
                detail to allow others to repeat, understand, critique and validate it, that same
                format falls short when it comes to communicating the complexity of modern
                research.</p>
            <p>For example, an early finding from the Reproducibility Project: Cancer Biology (RPCB)
                is that <a href="https://elifesciences.org/articles/23383">research methods are not
                    generally described in sufficient detail</a> to allow other researchers to
                faithfully repeat key experiments without engaging the original authors. And
                although engaging the author is an important part of the scientific conversation,
                the findings that form the very building blocks of scientific progress should
                ideally be communicated in a way that outlasts the original author’s memory.</p>
            <p>To this end, researchers today have access to a multitude of dedicated tools and
                services aimed at facilitating the sharing of specific methods and resources: <a
                        href="http://www.bio-protocol.org/">Bio-protocol</a> (a journal), <a
                        href="https://www.protocols.io/">Protocols.io</a> (an online repository and
                forum), and resource-specific initiatives such as <a href="https://www.addgene.org/"
                >AddGene</a> and <a href="http://www.chemicalprobes.org/">Chemical Probes</a>).
                Additionally, data and code repositories, and dedicated journals such as Scientific
                Data, <a href="http://joss.theoj.org/">JOSS</a> and <a
                        href="https://openresearchsoftware.metajnl.com/">JORS</a> provide platforms to
                more completely describe research data and software. Yet, while the abovementioned
                initiatives help researchers to improve the documentation of all the assets that lie
                behind a research finding, they also share one key obstacle to reproducibility: they
                are not integral to the research article itself.</p>
            <quote>
                <content>
                    <p>These days, data trails are often a morass of separate data and results and
                        code files in which no one knows which results were derived from which raw
                        data using which code files.</p>
                </content>
                <cite>Professor Charles Randy Gallistel, Rutgers University</cite>
            </quote>
        </content>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Supporting a reproducible document format</title>
        <content>
            <p>A reproducible document is one where any code used by the original researcher to
                compute an output (a graph, equation, table or statistical result) is embedded
                within the narrative describing the work.</p>
            <p>Reproducible document formats like <a
                    href="https://elifesciences.org/labs/cad57bcf/composing-reproducible-manuscripts-using-r-markdown"
            >R Markdown</a> and <a href="http://jupyter.org/">Jupyter Notebooks</a> help
                researchers organise both data and code into an understandable workflow that not
                only improves documentation for the authors themselves, making it faster to build on
                previous work when new data becomes available, but which also aids collaboration,
                training and reproducibility.</p>
            <quote>
                <content>
                    <p>Tools like Jupyter notebook enable a level of interaction that can transform
                        scientific communication. Exchange between authors and reviewers and,
                        ultimately, between authors and readers could be very focused on technical
                        aspects. This would counteract a trend by which papers are seen as tools to
                        advertise research work, rather than to enable other investigators to
                        proceed with research.</p>
                </content>
                <cite>Professor Vincenzo Carnevale, Temple University</cite>
            </quote>
            <p>But when submitting to a journal, authors today have to export their manuscripts in a
                flattened format (Word doc, PDF) or submit in LaTeX. This process strips code from
                being embedded into the narrative of the research into a separate asset. What
                started as a self-contained, fully reproducible document is transformed into a
                collection of linked assets.</p>
            <quote>
                <content>
                    <p>We are already composing our research manuscripts in a format that is
                        intimately paired with the methodology and data underlying the findings.
                        It's frustrating to have to convert these rich and reproducible documents
                        into flattened formats, such as PDF and Word documents, in order to satisfy
                        the needs of the traditional publishing workflow. I would like to see
                        publishers supporting me to share my work and data in the reproducible
                        formats I prepare them in.</p>
                </content>
                <cite>Dr Laurent Gatto, University of Cambridge</cite>
            </quote>
            <p>Earlier this year, <a
                    href="https://elifesciences.org/inside-elife/e832444e/innovation-understanding-the-demand-for-reproducible-research-articles"
            >researchers familiar with reproducible document tools told us</a> they were
                interested in being able to share and read research articles with features that
                support better code and data sharing as well as greater interactivity and
                executability:</p>
            <image>
                <alt>Bar graph showing researcher likelihood of using a feature such as downloading
                    data and code</alt>
                <attribution>
                    <p>Source: <a
                            href="https://elifesciences.org/inside-elife/e832444e/innovation-understanding-the-demand-for-reproducible-research-articles"
                    >https://elifesciences.org/inside-elife/e832444e/innovation-understanding-the-demand-for-reproducible-research-articles</a></p>
                </attribution>
                <iiif:info>https://iiif.elifesciences.org/journal-cms:content/2017-09/fig5-generaldemand.jpg/info.json</iiif:info>
                <source height="621" width="730" media-type="image/jpeg"
                        filename="fig5-generaldemand.jpg"
                >https://iiif.elifesciences.org/journal-cms:content/2017-09/fig5-generaldemand.jpg/full/full/0/default.jpg</source>
            </image>
            <p>As Dr Ithai Rabinowitch at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, notes, embedding data
                and code in an organised manner would not only aid reproducibility efforts, it could
                also “make science much more efficient as a community endeavour”. Professor Gary
                Bader, University of Toronto, adds:</p>
            <quote>
                <content>
                    <p>Having the code available for analysis workflows would really speed up
                        research. For instance, one could copy and improve a workflow for use with
                        another data set. We've seen this in my lab with the use of R/Jupyter
                        notebook.</p>
                </content>
            </quote>
            <p>Finally, providing a means for authors to enrich their research article in this way
                would recognise the researchers who invest resources in preparing these assets. This
                is a key point given <a href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4055448.v1">the
                    imbalance between effort and reward has been identified as a key barrier to
                    researchers adopting more open research practises</a>.</p>
        </content>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Reproducible Document Stack Project</title>
        <content>
            <p>We wish to support reproducible document formats from authoring through publication.
                A valuable step forward would be to enable researchers to publish the code and data
                behind their analyses in a form that can be easily examined, and thereby create
                figures and whole documents where users can faithfully reproduce key aspects of the
                work.</p>
            <p>As such, <a
                    href="https://elifesciences.org/for-the-press/e6038800/elife-supports-development-of-open-technology-stack-for-publishing-reproducible-manuscripts-online"
            >we are embarking on a project</a> with Substance and Stencila to develop the
                technology required to support the Reproducible Document through authoring, sharing
                and publication.</p>
            <quote>
                <content>
                    <p>We will have succeeded once any scientist can easily create a standardised
                        reproducible publication and submit it to a journal. Together with our
                        supporters we are building an open source toolset, to be used by authors,
                        journals and readers.</p>
                </content>
                <cite>Michael Aufreiter, Substance</cite>
            </quote>
            <p>The creation of an open standard for the exchange, submission and publication of
                reproducible documents is critical for widespread adoption by academic publishers,
                and will be beneficial for the discovery and persistence of research reported in
                this form. Therefore, a key output of this project will be a Reproducible Document
                Exchange Format, which will allow the data, code and computed outputs (graphs,
                statistical results, tables) embedded in a reproducible document to be recognised
                and presented online as <a
                        href="https://elifesciences.org/labs/e5737fd5/designing-progressive-enhancement-into-the-academic-manuscript"
                >an enhanced version</a> of the published research article. In order to do this,
                Substance is investigating how to represent these assets in JATS XML, the publishing
                standard through which research manuscripts are processed through the publishing
                workflow:</p>
            <code xml:space="preserve">&lt;fig id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Figure 1&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Biodiversity on Mars&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;alternatives&gt;
    &lt;code executable=&quot;yes&quot; specific-use=&quot;input&quot; language=&quot;mini&quot;&gt;
      bars(counts_by_species)
    &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;code specific-use=&quot;output&quot; language=&quot;json&quot;&gt;
      {
        &quot;execution_time&quot;: 322,
        &quot;value_type&quot;: &quot;plot-ly&quot;,
        &quot;value&quot;: {...}
      }
    &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;!-- static version for existing JATS toolchains --&gt;
    &lt;graphic xlink:href=&quot;89f8b53e361f.svg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;/alternatives&gt;
&lt;/fig&gt;</code>
            <p>This complements Substance's work to develop <a
                    href="https://elifesciences.org/labs/8de87c33/texture-an-open-science-manuscript-editor"
            >Texture</a>, an XML-based text editor for authoring, and contributions towards
                <a href="https://lens.elifesciences.org/about/">eLife Lens</a>, the side-by-side
                article reader.</p>
            <p>We recognise that these computational research tools are not the mainstay of all life
                sciences research. Efforts to encourage <a
                        href="https://medium.com/@_mql/reproducible-science-for-people-who-dont-code-5850abe806db"
                >greater adoption of reproducible research methods by researchers who are less
                    familiar with programming</a> are welcomed to aid interdisciplinary
                communications, and facilitate those who wish to learn code-based research
                practises. Substance and eLife are already supporting the development of <a
                        href="https://stenci.la/">Stencila</a>, an authoring platform and execution
                engine for reproducible documents that is targeted at researchers who are less
                comfortable with programming and more familiar with Microsoft Word and Excel.</p>
            <quote>
                <content>
                    <p>The calls for research to be reproducible are growing louder. But many of the
                        tools for reproducible research are code focussed and can be intimidating to
                        non-coders. We’re creating tools with the same intuitive, visual interfaces
                        that researchers are familiar with but built from the ground up with
                        reproducibility in mind. We want to create a platform that is accessible to
                        a greater range of scientists - without dumbing down their research or
                        restricting their ability to learn new computational methods.</p>
                </content>
                <cite>Nokome Bentley, Stencila</cite>
            </quote>
            <p>With intuitive text and spreadsheet authoring interfaces capable of producing XML
                documents, Stencila offers a platform to feed directly into the reproducible
                document publishing workflow.</p>
            <youtube height="720" width="1280">
                <id>PCRoc0JxRWg</id>
            </youtube>
            <p>In addition, we are interested in developing features that will enable readers to
                make the most of this enhanced article. Above all, the task of replicating an
                author’s original research – at least from a computational and analysis angle –
                should be trivial from the reader’s standpoint.</p>
            <p>To meet the needs of researchers, the project will need to address several key
                technological considerations, including:</p>
            <list prefix="bullet">
                <item><b>The diversity of programming environments used in research must be
                    supported</b> – a variety of languages and environments are used to perform
                    computations in research, from Python and R, to Bash and Matlab, and sometimes
                    multiple languages are combined in a single workflow. The Reproducible Document
                    Exchange Format will be designed with applications like Jupyter and R Studio (a
                    popular R Markdown authoring tool) in mind, but ultimately be platform-agnostic
                    to enable researchers freedom of choice in their own workflow.</item>
                <item><b>Researchers should be able to follow their current workflows </b>– the rich
                    ecosystem of platforms and tools for conducting, storing, documenting and
                    sharing computational research is a resource that we intend to build on.
                    Further, some scripts and data are too complex to sit within a reproducible
                    document. Where possible, we aim to support as many use cases and workflows as
                    possible, and we welcome input from the community to help us to understand these
                    use cases (email <a href="mailto:innovation@elifesciences.org"
                    >innovation@elifesciences.org</a>).</item>
                <item><b>Composing reproducible manuscripts should be easy</b> – current authoring
                    tools such as Microsoft Word are popular for a reason: What You See Is What You
                    Get (WYSIWYG). We intend to support tools that make authoring and consumption of
                    computationally reproducible documents as intuitive as possible for the user. It
                    was with this principle in mind that <a
                            href="https://elifesciences.org/labs/fc2e10b3/redesigning-an-online-scientific-journal-from-the-article-up"
                    >we recently redesigned our online journal</a>.</item>
            </list>
        </content>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Get involved</title>
        <content>
            <p>We are at the beginning of the process to develop a complete publishing solution to
                support the Reproducible Document envisioned above. We expect this process to take
                at least 12 months.</p>
            <p>We are open to your input and feedback throughout, whether about the concept or
                regarding specific elements. Please consider commenting publicly on this blogpost
                using <a href="https://hypothes.is">Hypothes.is</a>, or emailing us directly at <a
                        href="mailto:innovation@elifesciences.org">innovation@elifesciences.org</a>. For
                more news, please sign up for our <a
                        href="https://crm.elifesciences.org/crm/node/8?_ga=2.196309225.471549536.1503402080-303271206.1463581989"
                >technology and innovation newsletter</a>.</p>
            <p>For specific elements contributing towards this project, please see:</p>
            <list prefix="bullet">
                <item>Texture is an open format manuscript editor: the code is open source at <a
                        href="https://github.com/substance/texture"
                >https://github.com/substance/texture</a></item>
                <item>Stencila is a office suite for reproducible research: it is being developed
                    openly at <a href="https://github.com/stencila/stencila"
                    >https://github.com/stencila/stencila</a> and you can participate in
                    discussions at <a href="https://community.stenci.la/"
                    >https://community.stenci.la/</a></item>
            </list>
        </content>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Future considerations</title>
        <content>
            <p>The ultimate goal of this project is to enable researchers to share their research
                manuscripts in a reproducible format. This will complement existing practises to
                share research data and code, and readers will remain free to use the assets as they
                wish. However, this project will also open up new avenues for innovation, including
                the executability of articles online, and the potential to capitalise on
                reproducible resources during peer review.</p>
            <p>The idea of supporting executable notebooks is not new. In 2014, <a
                    href="http://www.nature.com/news/interactive-notebooks-sharing-the-code-1.16261"
            >Nature piloted a feature</a> that supported an online interactive iPython
                notebook (now Jupyter notebook). This was a popular feature, likely due to the
                novelty, with <a
                        href="https://developer.rackspace.com/blog/how-did-we-serve-more-than-20000-ipython-notebooks-for-nature/"
                >more than 20,000 notebook runs</a> computed. The team behind Authorea, the
                online collaborative authoring platform, <a
                        href="https://www.authorea.com/users/3/articles/156875-the-authorea-open-product-roadmap"
                >continue to add</a> features that enable authors to <a
                        href="https://www.authorea.com/users/3/articles/3904-data-driven-interactive-science-with-d3-js-plots-and-ipython-notebooks/_show_article"
                >include dynamic and interactive plots</a> in their manuscripts and to highlight
                the source data underlying a figure. How these features could be supported by the
                ultimate publisher of the peer-reviewed work remains to be addressed, but <a
                        href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2014-07/fo1-fbs073014.php">F1000
                    Research has piloted similar features</a> and continues to experiment along
                these lines. Further, journals in other domains are responding to the needs of their
                own computational research communities: <a href="https://distill.pub/about/"
                >Distill</a>, an online journal for machine learning research, includes a
                ‘reactive diagram’ feature and, in some articles, readers can even <a
                        href="http://distill.pub/2016/handwriting/">input data to trial an
                    algorithm</a>.</p>
            <p>Any third-party review of data and code assets is challenging. Currently, reviewers
                have to in many cases take the authors at their word that the code and algorithms
                they employed in their work are robust. At Nature Neuroscience, the efficacy of code
                sharing is currently under investigation via <a
                        href="http://www.nature.com/neuro/journal/v20/n6/full/nn.4579.html">a pilot to
                    review the code used to compute key figures in new articles</a>. We hope that
                offering a means to share reproducible documents will help to incentivise the
                sharing of demonstrably reusable data and code underlying a research article.
                Further, opening up the means to support the submission of research in a
                reproducible format could assist interested reviewers to reproduce computations with
                as minimal extra effort as is feasible.</p>
        </content>
    </section>
    <p>For the latest in innovation, eLife Labs and new open-source tools, sign up for our <a
            href="https://crm.elifesciences.org/crm/node/8?_ga=2.213152084.1156933223.1498463747-1005832603.1488200227"
    >technology and innovation newsletter</a>. You can also follow <a
            href="https://twitter.com/eLifeInnovation?lang=en">@eLifeInnovation</a> on Twitter. We
        welcome comments and questions, so please comment using <a href="https://web.hypothes.is/"
        >Hypothes.is</a>.</p>

</body>
