<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../article.rng"?>

<article xmlns="http://libero.pub" xmlns:elife="http://elifesciences.org" xml:lang="en">

    <id>00569</id>
    <doi>10.7554/eLife.00569</doi>
    <title>The genome sequence of the colonial chordate, <elife:genome>Botryllus
            schlosseri</elife:genome></title>
    <abstract id="abstract" doi="10.7554/eLife.00569.001">
        <p><i>Botryllus schlosseri</i> is a colonial urochordate that follows the chordate plan of
            development following sexual reproduction, but invokes a stem cell-mediated budding
            program during subsequent rounds of asexual reproduction. As urochordates are considered
            to be the closest living invertebrate relatives of vertebrates, they are ideal subjects
            for whole genome sequence analyses. Using a novel method for high-throughput sequencing
            of eukaryotic genomes, we sequenced and assembled 580 Mbp of the <i>B. schlosseri</i>
            genome. The genome assembly is comprised of nearly 14,000 intron-containing predicted
            genes, and 13,500 intron-less predicted genes, 40% of which could be confidently
            parceled into 13 (of 16 haploid) chromosomes. A comparison of homologous genes between
                <i>B. schlosseri</i> and other diverse taxonomic groups revealed genomic events
            underlying the evolution of vertebrates and lymphoid-mediated immunity. The <i>B.
                schlosseri</i> genome is a community resource for studying alternative modes of
            reproduction, natural transplantation reactions, and stem cell-mediated
            regeneration.</p>
    </abstract>
    <elife:digest id="digest" doi="10.7554/eLife.00569.002">
        <elife:p>The tunicates are an evolutionary group that includes species such as sea squirts
            and sea tulips. Their name comes from the structure known as a ‘tunic’ that surrounds
            their sac-like bodies. As marine filter feeders, tunicates obtain nutrients by straining
            food particles from water, and they can live either alone or in colonies depending on
            the species. Charles Darwin suggested that tunicates may be the key to understanding the
            evolution of vertebrates, and indeed today they are regarded as the closest living
            relatives of this group.</elife:p>
        <p>Colonial tunicates can reproduce either sexually, or asexually by budding. Compatible
            colonies have the ability to recognize one another and to fuse their blood vessels to
            form a single organism, whereas incompatible colonies reject one another and remain
            separate. This recognition process bears some resemblance to the rejection of foreign
            organ transplants in mammals.</p>
        <p>Here, Voskoboynik and co-workers present the first genome sequence of a colonial
            tunicate, <i>Botryllus schlosseri.</i> They used a novel sequencing approach that
            significantly increased the length of a DNA molecule that can be determined by
            next-generation sequencing, and allowed large DNA repeat regions to be easily resolved.
            In total, they sequenced 580 million base pairs of DNA, which they estimate contains
            roughly 27,000 genes.</p>
        <p>By comparing the <i>B. schlosseri</i> genome with those of a number of vertebrates,
            Voskoboynik et al. identified multiple <i>B. schlosseri</i> genes that also participate
            in the development and functioning of the vertebrate eye, heart, and auditory system, as
            well as others that may have contributed to the evolution of the immune system and of
            blood cells. The genome of <i>B. schlosseri</i> thus provides an important new tool for
            studying the genetic basis of the evolution of vertebrates.</p>
    </elife:digest>

</article>
