<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../../front.rng"?>

<front xmlns="http://libero.pub" xmlns:scielo="http://scielo.org" xml:lang="en">

    <id>0065-1737-azm-31-03-0367</id>
    <title>Damage evaluation of (Lepidoptera: Tortricidae) (Heinrich),
        structural parameters and natural regeneration in Pinus nelsonii (Shaw) and
        P. cembroides ( Zucc.) in Miquihuana, Tamaulipas</title>
    <abstract id="abstract">
        <p>The present study aims to determine the damage intensity of the pinyon pitch
            nodule moth, Retinia arizonensis and their possible relationship to some
            structural parameters: stem diameter, height and coverage, as well as the
            natural regeneration of Pinus cembroides and P. nelsonii. For their evaluation,
            sites with 2,500 m<sup>2</sup> of each species were located. A total of 136
            individuals of P. cembroides were recorded, with an average damage of 10.5%
            (±8.1 SD) in the terminal buds. In P. nelsonii, a total of 47 individuals
            were found, 46 exhibited damage from R. arizonensis, averaging 4.8% (±4.5
            SD), twice less than P. cembroides. We used the Kruskal-Wallis
            (H-Chi<sup>2</sup>) to assess the damage of R. arizonensis between species,
            marked significant difference (p &lt; 0.001) was observed. Relating to the
            structure, P. cembroides showed the following mean values: stem diameter = 10.7
            cm (±8.0 SD), height = 2.9 m (±1.0 SD) and coverage = 3.0
            m<sup>2</sup> (±1.8 SD). With respect to P. nelsonii, these were:
            stem diameter = 10.7 cm (±4.3), height = 3.6 m (±0.8) and coverage
            m<sup>2</sup> = 4.2 (±1.8), these variables showed wide statistical
            differences (p &lt; 0.001). When measuring the association of R. arizonensis
            damage, with the structural variables, P. cembroides showed a positive marginal
            correlation with the variables height, diameter and covering with r<sup>2</sup>
            = 0.12, 0.16 and 0.18, respectively (p &lt; 0.001). However, P. nelsonii
            expressed non-significant correlations among R. arizonensis damage with the
            structural parameters. The combined influence of the three structural variables
            (multiple correlation r<sup>2</sup>) of R. arizonensis damage, was mostly
            explained in P. cembroides with r<sup>2</sup> value of 0.19 highly significant
            (p &lt; 0.001). In relation to P. nelsonii, the structural variables influenced
            on damage percentage of R. arizonensis were not significant (p = 0.128). Natural
            regeneration showed percentage participation (relative to adult trees) of 20.6%
            for P. cembroides and 42.5% for P. nelsonii with mean height of 13.9 cm
            (±12.6) and 28.4 cm (±20.0) in P. cembroides and P. nelsonii,
            respectively.</p>
    </abstract>

</front>
