<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../body.rng"?>

<body xmlns="http://libero.pub" xmlns:ms="http://microsimulation.org"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xml:lang="en">

    <section id="s1">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <content>
            <p>How does the structure of an economic system affect its performance? By
                &#x2018;structure&#x2019; we mean the way in which different constituent parts are
                related to each other in terms of communication and decision-making. Most economies
                have a complex mix of different structures including markets, firms, and government
                agencies of various kinds. Despite their differences, all these structures face the
                common problem of coordinating the activities of constituent parts who possess
                private information. There are two ways in which markets, firms, and government
                agencies solve coordination problems: centralization and decentralization. The
                Chicago Mercantile Exchange has a central clearing house and quotation system (<a
                    href="#bib19">Millo et al., 2005</a>), but Torino&#x2019;s farmers market has no
                such central structure. Alfred Sloan granted considerable autonomy to division
                managers in General Motors (<a href="#bib27">Sloan, 1964</a>), but such autonomy
                does not exist in all firms (<a href="#bib17">Love et al., 2002</a>). The United
                States government consists of various federal, state, and local departments with
                overlapping jurisdictions (<a href="#bib16">Liesbet and Gary, 2003</a>). The North
                Korean government is presumably largely centrally organized with organs like the
                &#x2018;Central People&#x2019;s Committee&#x2019; and the &#x2018;State Planning
                Committee&#x2019;. As to how the structure of an economic system affects its
                performance is a fundamental theoretical question with a bearing on the
                microstructure of markets, the internal organization of firms, and the structure of
                governments.</p>
            <p>In this paper, we compare the performance of a centralized and a decentralized system
                in solving a simple coordination problem when their constituent parts make errors in
                communicating private information. We find that the decentralized system is more
                robust than the centralized system to communication errors. But the centralized
                system takes less time than the decentralized system to create coordination. Our
                analysis sheds light on the influence of communication technology on organizational
                forms, the greater variability of autocratic societies compared to democratic
                societies, the variation in economic organization with product type, and the
                preference for centralized organization in urgencies like war.</p>
            <p>We study a simple ordering problem in which agents are indexed by a number and
                randomly placed on a line. The coordination problem is to order the agents according
                to their numbers, with the least numbered agent on left and highest numbered on the
                right. In the centralized system, agents communicate their numbers to a central
                authority, who uses the information to order the agents. In the decentralized
                system, agents communicate their numbers to neighbours and swap positions if the
                number of the agent on left is more than the number of the agent on right. Agents
                probabilistically make errors in communicating private information in the
                centralized system and the decentralized system. We find that the decentralized
                system is more robust to communication errors than the centralized system. This is
                because the centralized system of coordination involves a strong-dependence between
                the information communicated by constituent parts (<a href="#bib26">Simon,
                1962</a>). Errors in the information communicated by one agent to the
                central-coordinator negatively affects the usefulness of the information
                communicated by other agents to the central-coordinator. The decentralized system on
                the other hand involves weak-dependence between the information communicated by
                constituent parts. Errors in the information communicated by one agent to its
                neighbour has a negligible effect on the usefulness of the information communicated
                by other agents to their neighbours. The localization of decision-making in the
                decentralized system limits the impact of communication errors on the
                system&#x2019;s performance. The strong-dependence between the information
                communicated by different agents in the centralized system and the weak-dependence
                in the decentralized system is a consequence of the difference in structure of
                communication and decision-making in the two systems.</p>
            <p><a href="#bib30">von Neumann, 1951</a> illustrates the idea of strong-dependence and
                weak-dependence with the following analogy. Imagine placing your hand in a tub of
                water at 80&#x00B0;C. There are two ways to communicate this information from the
                nerve endings in your hand to your brain. One way is to convey the temperature in
                binary form. Another way is the counting method, where one count is communicated for
                each 1&#x00B0;C. Interestingly, the human nervous system uses a mechanism roughly
                akin to the counting method. This despite the fact that the counting method involves
                communicating orders of magnitude more information than the binary method. <a
                    href="#bib30">von Neumann, 1951</a>, p. 101) speculates on why the human nervous
                system uses the counting method: &#x201C;...the counting method has a high stability
                and safety from error. If you express a number of the order of million by counting
                and miss a count, the result is only irrelevantly changed. If you express it by
                (decimal or binary) expansion, a single error in a single digit may vitiate the
                entire result.&#x2019;</p>
            <p>80&#x00B0;C in binary is 1010000. If the first digit is erroneously reported as 0,
                the temperature conveyed is 16&#x00B0;C. The usefulness of correct information
                conveyed by all other digits is vitiated by a single error. In contrast to the
                binary method, in the counting method the absence of a count has a negligible effect
                on the usefulness of the other counts. If a count is missed, the temperature
                conveyed is 79&#x00B0;C. There is strong-dependence among the digits in the binary
                method, but weak-dependence among the counts in the counting method. The principle
                of strong and weak dependence are at play in centralized and decentralized systems,
                and is the cause of the greater robustness of the decentralized system to
                communication errors.</p>
            <p>Though the decentralized system is more robust to communication errors, the
                centralized system uses less time to create coordination. The absence of a central
                decision-making unit means that the decentralized system has to muddle through
                numerous local communications and decisions, all of which takes time. The very
                structural feature that makes the decentralized system robust also makes it slow.
                Centralization is preferable to decentralization when there is urgency and when
                constituent parts are less likely to make errors in communicating private
                information.</p>
            <p>Our paper is related to the literature on the architecture of economic systems (<a
                    href="#bib7">Bolton and Farrell, 1990</a>; <a href="#bib11">Guerini et al.,
                    2016</a>; <a href="#bib13">Hayek, 1945</a>; <a href="#bib15">Lange, 1936</a>; <a
                    href="#bib25">Sah and Stiglitz, 1986</a>), the literature on the internal
                organization of firms (<a href="#bib1">Acemoglu et al., 2007</a>; <a href="#bib3"
                    >Alonso et al., 2008</a>; <a href="#bib18">Maskin et al., 2000</a>; <a
                    href="#bib28">Stein, 2002</a>), and the literature on the structure of
                governments (<a href="#bib10">Egeberg, 2007</a>; <a href="#bib14">Landau, 1969</a>;
                    <a href="#bib23">Peters, 1998</a>). The literature on the architecture of
                economic systems began with the socialist calculation debate between Otto Neurath
                and Ludwig von Mises, though the modern strand originates from the contributions of
                    <a href="#bib13">Hayek, 1945</a> claimed the market system is superior to
                communist central planning in using dispersed information to coordinate the
                activities of different agents. <a href="#bib15">Lange, 1936</a> argued central
                planning can attain efficient allocation of resources by mimicking the price system.
                While the relative advantages of price, shadow-price, and non-price mechanisms of
                coordination are important, &#x2018;there is more at stake in the choice of an
                economic system&#x2019; (<a href="#bib25">Sah and Stiglitz, 1986</a>), p. 726). One
                of the differences between centralized and decentralized economic systems is how
                they perform in the presence of communication errors. The difference between the
                Soviet centrally planned economy and the US economy is not only one of the extent to
                which they use price signals to communicate economic information, but also the
                structures through which they communicate information. These structures influence
                the performance of the two systems when economic signals contain noise.</p>
            <p>The question of the architecture of economic systems is not limited to understanding
                the differences between economic systems. It also pertains to understanding the
                differences in the mix of markets, firms, and government agencies within an economic
                system (<a href="#bib12">Hall and Soskice, 2001</a>). Our paper is a close cousin of
                    <a href="#bib25">Sah and Stiglitz, 1986</a>, <a href="#bib7">Bolton and Farrell,
                    1990</a>, and <a href="#bib11">Guerini et al., 2016</a>. While we study the
                consequence of errors in the communication of information, <a href="#bib25">Sah and
                    Stiglitz, 1986</a> study the consequence of errors in the processing of
                information in alternate economic arrangements. <a href="#bib7">Bolton and Farrell,
                    1990</a> study the problem of entry in a system with two agents with differing
                costs. Bolton and Farrell argue that decentralization involves duplication and
                delay. We too find decentralization involves delay, but for a reason different from
                Bolton and Farrell&#x2019;s. In our model, the decentralized system takes more time
                than the centralized system because the decentralized system has to muddle through
                numerous local communications and decision-making. In Bolton and Farrell&#x2019;s
                model, delay occurs because agents do not communicate with each other in the
                decentralized system. <a href="#bib11">Guerini et al., 2016</a> study the
                macroeconomic performance of a centralized and a decentralized protocol of search
                and matching. They find that the centralized protocol produces full-employment,
                whereas the decentralized protocol produces unemployment. We believe their results
                may change if the coordinator in the centralized protocol has to collect private
                information from agents who make communication errors.</p>
            <p>In the literature on the role of information in shaping the internal organization of
                firms, our paper is related to <a href="#bib28">Stein, 2002</a>, <a href="#bib18"
                    >Maskin et al., 2000</a>, <a href="#bib1">Acemoglu et al., 2007</a>, and <a
                    href="#bib3">Alonso et al., 2008</a>. Our paper shares some ingredients with
                these papers, while differing from them in important respects. In <a href="#bib28"
                    >Stein, 2002</a> model agents do not communicate private information in the
                decentralized system. In <a href="#bib1">Acemoglu et al. (2007)</a> model agents do
                not communicate private information in the centralized system. In contrast to Stein
                and Acemoglu et al., we study the differences in the performance of centralized and
                decentralized systems due to the differences in their structures of communication
                and decision-making. <a href="#bib18">Maskin et al., 2000</a> and <a href="#bib3"
                    >Alonso et al., 2008</a> study the differences in performances of systems
                because their structure influences the incentives to communicate private
                information. Our paper studies the differences in performance of systems even when
                their structures do not influence incentives. Matters other than incentives matter.
                All this means that even when our conclusions concur with those of other papers in
                the literature, the reasoning behind the conclusions differ. For instance, <a
                    href="#bib28">Stein, 2002</a> concludes decentralization is preferable when
                information is difficult to communicate. This is similar to our conclusion that
                decentralization is preferable when there is a greater likelihood of communication
                errors. After all, information is difficult to communicate when there are
                communication errors. However, the reasoning behind Stein&#x2019;s conclusion
                differs from ours. In Stein&#x2019;s case, decentralization is preferable when
                information is difficult to communicate because no communication is necessary in the
                decentralized system. In our case, decentralization is preferable when information
                is difficult to communicate because the localization of communication limits the
                consequences of communication errors on the system&#x2019;s performance. Our
                contribution to the literature on firms is that the internal structure of firms
                matters because it determines the robustness of firms to employees&#x2019;
                communication errors and the speed with which firms can coordinate the activities of
                its employees.</p>
            <p>Our paper is also related to the literature on the structure and performance of
                governments (<a href="#bib6">Bendor et al., 2001</a>; <a href="#bib22">Ostrom et
                    al., 1961</a>; <a href="#bib21">Ostrom, 1999</a>). <a href="#bib22">Ostrom et
                    al., 1961</a> argue that the presence of multiple government agencies with
                overlapping jurisdictions is not a pathological phenomenon, nor can the problems
                posed by the multiplicity of government agencies be resolved by centralization. The
                contribution by <a href="#bib22">Ostrom et al., 1961</a> sparked an interesting
                literature on the origin and performance of alternate structures of government. This
                literature studied a variety of ways in which structure affects performance,
                including the relation between norms and governance structures (<a href="#bib21"
                    >Ostrom, 1999</a>), and the influence of government structure on incentives to
                truthfully reveal information (<a href="#bib6">Bendor et al., 2001</a>). Our
                analysis suggests that the structure of government influences performance, even when
                the structure does not influence social norms and incentives. Most governments have
                a rich and intricate framework for negotiation and adjudication between different
                agencies. Negotiation and adjudication involves error-prone communication. Our model
                suggests that the structure of government influences its robustness to error-prone
                communication between different agencies and the speed with which governments can
                execute tasks. Our paper is organized as follows. Section 2 presents the model.
                Section 3 reports and explains the results of the model. Section 4 discusses the
                implications of the ideas developed in this paper. Section 5 offers concluding
                remarks.</p>
        </content>
    </section>
    <section id="s2">
        <title>The model</title>
        <content>
            <p>Imagine a set of <i>n</i> agents numbered from 1 to <i>n</i>. No two agents have the
                same number. The agents are randomly placed on a line segment; they are in no
                particular order. The coordination problem is to order the agents from 1 to <i>n</i>
                from left to right, where each agent&#x2019;s number is one greater than the number
                of its neighbour on the left and one less than the number of its neighbour on the
                right. The first agent does not have a left neighbour and the last agent does not
                have a right neighbour.</p>
            <p>There are two ways to order the agents: a centralized system and a decentralized
                system. In the centralized system, each agent conveys its number to a
                central-coordinator. The central-coordinator orders the agents on a line segment.
                For instance, if an agent communicates its number as 3, the central-coordinator
                places the agent in position 3 on the line segment. The central-coordinator orders
                the agents as the agents communicate their numbers to the central-coordinator.</p>
            <p>The decentralized system works differently. Each time step, pairs of neighbouring
                agents are randomly selected. Within each pair, agents share information about each
                other&#x2019;s numbers. If the agent on the left reports a number greater than the
                agent on the right, the agents swap positions, otherwise the agents remain in their
                current positions. Over time, the agents incrementally order themselves.</p>
            <p>Agents make errors in communicating their numbers, i.e. with some probability an
                agent conveys an incorrect number. When an agent makes a communication error, it
                reports a random number between 1 and <i>n</i> rather than its true number.
                Communication errors create problems in the centralized system and the decentralized
                system. In the centralized system, the central-coordinator places the agent who
                reports an incorrect number in an incorrect location. Further problems arise because
                another agent cannot be placed in that location. For instance, if <i>agent 3</i>
                reports number 5 and is placed in location 5, <i>agent 5</i> cannot be placed in
                location 5. When an agent reports a number whose location is occupied, the
                central-coordinator places it in the nearest empty location.</p>
            <p>In the decentralized system, communication errors cause agents to wrongly swap
                positions, i.e. a greater number agent may move left and a lower number agent may
                move right. Suppose <i>agent 3</i> and <i>agent 5</i> are neighbours with <i>agent
                    3</i> on the left of <i>agent 5</i>. Upon activation the agents communicate
                their numbers to each other. <i>Agent 3</i> correctly communicates its number, but
                    <i>agent 5</i> makes an error and communicates 2 as its number. The two agents
                swap positions. <i>Agent 5</i> moves left and <i>agent 3</i> moves right, thereby
                decreasing the system&#x2019;s coordination.</p>
            <p>In the centralized system, at the first time step all <i>n</i> agents communicate
                their numbers to the central-coordinator. The central-coordinator orders the agents
                at the end of the first time step using the collected information. In the
                decentralized system, at each time step, <i>n</i> neighbouring pairs of agents are
                randomly activated. The activated agents exchange information and swap positions if
                necessary. In the decentralized system, agents incrementally order themselves over
                many time steps.</p>
            <p>The coordination in the system is measured using the formula</p>
            <mathml id="equ1">
                <label>(1)</label>
                <mml:math id="m1">
                    <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                        <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                                <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext>
                            <mml:munderover>
                                <mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x2211;</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                    <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                                </mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:munderover>
                            <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>&#x2013;</mml:mo>
                            <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mrow>
                                        <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                                    </mml:mrow>
                                </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mstyle>
                </mml:math>
            </mathml>
            <p>where <mml:math id="inf1">
                    <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                </mml:math> is the number of <i>agent i</i> and <mml:math id="inf2">
                    <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>l</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:msub>
                </mml:math> is the number of the location of <i>agent i</i>. Coordination is the
                negative mean of the absolute value of the differences between the numbers of agents
                and the numbers of their respective locations. For instance, if <i>agent 3</i> is at
                location 5, the absolute value of difference is 2. The sum of these differences is
                divided by the total number of agents and multiplied by negative one to measure
                coordination. Zero indicates perfect coordination, lower values of <i>C</i> indicate
                lesser coordination. The model is built in Python programming language. Model code
                is available at <a href="https://bitbucket.org/VipinVeetil/CoordinationSystems"
                    >https://bitbucket.org/VipinVeetil/CoordinationSystems</a>.</p>
            <p>Section three reports the results from numerous simulations of the model. In each
                simulation, the centralized system is run for one time step because it orders the
                agents after the first time step. In each simulation, the decentralized system is
                run for 1000 time steps, and its coordination is measured at the end of the last
                time step. <a href="#fig1">Figures 1</a>, <a href="#fig2">2</a>, <a href="#fig3"
                    >3</a> and <a href="#fig4">4</a> report the results from 10<sup>4</sup>
                simulations of the centralized system and the decentralized system for each
                probability of error in the range [0, 1] with increments of 0.01. Therefore, <a
                    href="#fig1">Figures 1</a>, <a href="#fig2">2</a>, <a href="#fig3">3</a> and <a
                    href="#fig4">4</a> summarize the results from 2 &#x00D7; 10<sup>6</sup>
                simulations. <a href="#fig5">Figure 5</a> reports the results from 10<sup>3</sup>
                simulations of the centralized system and the decentralized system for each number
                of agents in the interval [10, 1000] with increments of 10. Therefore, <a
                    href="#fig5">Figure 5</a> summarizes the outcome of 2 &#x00D7; 10<sup>5</sup>
                simulations.</p>
        </content>
    </section>
    <section id="s3">
        <title>The model</title>
        <content>
            <p>Result 1 shows that the centralized system has lower mean coordination and a greater
                variance of coordination than the decentralized system. <a href="#fig1">Figure 1</a>
                shows that the mean coordination of the centralized system is less than the mean of
                the decentralized system. <a href="#fig2">Figure 2</a> shows that the variance of
                the coordination of the centralized system is greater than the variance in the
                decentralized system. <a href="#fig3">Figure 3</a> presents box-plots using all the
                data points used to compute mean and variance plotted in <a href="#fig1">Figures
                    1</a> and <a href="#fig2">2</a>. <a href="#fig4">Figure 4</a> plots histograms
                of the coordination of the centralized system and the decentralized system for four
                different probabilities of communication errors. Like <a href="#fig1">Figures 1</a>
                and <a href="#fig2">2</a>, <a href="#fig3">Figures 3</a> and <a href="#fig4">4</a>
                show that the centralized system has a lower mean and a greater variance than the
                decentralized system.</p>
            <p>The centralized system has a lower mean than the decentralized system for the
                following reason. In the centralized system, an individual agent&#x2019;s
                communication error has a significant impact on the coordination created by the
                central-coordinator. One agent&#x2019;s misplacement has the potential to produce a
                cascade of misplacements. Suppose <i>agent 3</i> communicates number 5 and is placed
                at location 5. <i>Agent 5</i> makes no communication error, but <i>agent 5</i>
                cannot be placed in location 5 because location 5 is occupied by <i>agent 3</i>. The
                central coordinator places <i>agent 5</i> at the nearest empty location, say
                location 7. This means <i>agent 7</i> cannot be placed at location 7. <i>Agent
                    3&#x2019;s</i> communication error has the potential to create the misplacements
                of other agents, even when other agents do not make communication errors. In the
                centralized system, the communication errors of some agents can vitiate the
                usefulness of correct information communicated by many agents. This is due to the
                very structure of ordering in the centralized system.</p>
            <p>In contrast to the centralized system, in the decentralized system an individual
                agent&#x2019;s communication error has a local impact; a lower number agent may move
                to the right of a higher number agent, thereby producing a minor decrease in the
                decentralized system&#x2019;s coordination. In the decentralized system, the impact
                of an individual agent&#x2019;s communication error on the system&#x2019;s
                performance is limited. Suppose <i>agent 8</i> and <i>agent 10</i> are neighbours
                with <i>agent 8</i> on the left of <i>agent 10</i>. Upon activation they communicate
                their numbers to each other. <i>Agent 8</i> correctly communicates 8 as its number,
                but <i>agent 10</i> makes an error and communicates 5 as its number. The two agents
                swap positions. <i>Agent 8</i> is now on the right of <i>agent 10</i>. The
                system&#x2019;s coordination decreases due to <i>agent 8&#x2019;s</i> communication
                error. However, the communication error of <i>agent 8</i> has no impact on the
                information communicated and decisions made by other pairs of agents. The
                decentralized system has a greater mean than the centralized system because the
                structure of communication in decentralized system dampens the impact of
                communication errors.</p>
            <p>The centralized system has a greater variance of coordination than the decentralized
                system because the performance of the centralized system is more dependent on the
                specifics of who does what. In the centralized system, an individual agent&#x2019;s
                communication error can trigger a cascade of misplacements of other agents. The size
                of a cascade due to an agent&#x2019;s communication error depends on the exact
                error, the messages communicated by other agents, and the position of the agent who
                makes the communication error. These factors vary across simulations and so does the
                performance of the centralized system. In contrast to the centralized system, in the
                decentralized system the randomness generated by the error-prone behaviour of agents
                is dampened by the structure of interactions; decentralized interactions dilute the
                specifics of who does what.</p>
            <figure>
                <asset>
                    <label>Figure 1.</label>
                    <image id="fig1">
                        <title>Mean of coordination in the centralized and the decentralized
                            system.</title>
                        <caption>
                            <p>Note: In the centralized system, each agent conveys its number to a
                                central-coordinator. The central-coordinator orders the agents on a
                                line segment. In the decentralized system, at each time step, pairs
                                of neighbouring agents are randomly selected. Within each pair,
                                agents share information about each other&#x2019;s numbers. If the
                                agent on the left reports a number greater than the agent on the
                                right, the agents swap positions, otherwise the agents remain in
                                their present positions. Agents make errors in communicating their
                                numbers, i.e. with some probability an agent conveys an incorrect
                                number. Coordination is the negative mean of the absolute value of
                                the differences between the numbers of agents and the numbers of
                                their respective locations. The sum of these differences is divided
                                by the total number of agents and multiplied by negative one to
                                measure coordination. Zero indicates perfect coordination, lower
                                values of C indicate lesser coordination.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <source height="1" width="1" media-type="application/postscript"
                            >http://www.microsimulation.org/IJM/fig1</source>
                    </image>
                </asset>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <asset>
                    <label>Figure 2.</label>
                    <image id="fig2">
                        <title>Variance of coordination in the centralized and the decentralized
                            system.</title>
                        <caption>
                            <p>Note: In the centralized system, each agent conveys its number to a
                                central-coordinator. The central-coordinator orders the agents on a
                                line segment. In the decentralized system, at each time step, pairs
                                of neighbouring agents are randomly selected. Within each pair,
                                agents share information about each other&#x2019;s numbers. If the
                                agent on the left reports a number greater than the agent on the
                                right, the agents swap positions, otherwise the agents remain in
                                their present positions. Agents make errors in communicating their
                                numbers, i.e. with some probability an agent conveys an incorrect
                                number. Coordination is the negative mean of the absolute value of
                                the differences between the numbers of agents and the numbers of
                                their respective locations. The sum of these differences is divided
                                by the total number of agents and multiplied by negative one to
                                measure coordination. Zero indicates perfect coordination, lower
                                values of C indicate lesser coordination.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <source height="1" width="1" media-type="application/postscript"
                            >http://www.microsimulation.org/IJM/fig2</source>
                    </image>
                </asset>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <asset>
                    <label>Figure 3.</label>
                    <image id="fig3">
                        <title>Boxplots of coordination in the centralized and the decentralized
                            system.</title>
                        <caption>
                            <p>Note: In the centralized system, each agent conveys its number to a
                                central-coordinator. The central-coordinator orders the agents on a
                                line segment. In the decentralized system, at each time step, pairs
                                of neighbouring agents are randomly selected. Within each pair,
                                agents share information about each other&#x2019;s numbers. If the
                                agent on the left reports a number greater than the agent on the
                                right, the agents swap positions, otherwise the agents remain in
                                their present positions. Agents make errors in communicating their
                                numbers, i.e. with some probability an agent conveys an incorrect
                                number. Coordination is the negative mean of the absolute value of
                                the differences between the numbers of agents and the numbers of
                                their respective locations. The sum of these differences is divided
                                by the total number of agents and multiplied by negative one to
                                measure coordination. Zero indicates perfect coordination, lower
                                values of C indicate lesser coordination.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <source height="1" width="1" media-type="application/postscript"
                            >http://www.microsimulation.org/IJM/fig3</source>
                    </image>
                </asset>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <asset>
                    <label>Figure 4.</label>
                    <image id="fig4">
                        <title>Histograms of coordination of the centralized and decentralized
                            systems with different probabilities of error.</title>
                        <caption>
                            <p>Note: In the centralized system, each agent conveys its number to a
                                central-coordinator. The central-coordinator orders the agents on a
                                line segment. In the decentralized system, at each time step, pairs
                                of neighbouring agents are randomly selected. Within each pair,
                                agents share information about each other&#x2019;s numbers. If the
                                agent on the left reports a number greater than the agent on the
                                right, the agents swap positions, otherwise the agents remain in
                                their present positions. Agents make errors in communicating their
                                numbers, i.e. with some probability an agent conveys an incorrect
                                number. Coordination is the negative mean of the absolute value of
                                the differences between the numbers of agents and the numbers of
                                their respective locations. The sum of these differences is divided
                                by the total number of agents and multiplied by negative one to
                                measure coordination. Zero indicates perfect coordination, lower
                                values of C indicate lesser coordination.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <source height="1" width="1" media-type="application/postscript"
                            >http://www.microsimulation.org/IJM/fig4</source>
                    </image>
                </asset>
            </figure>
            <p>Result 2 shows that the decentralized system takes more time than the centralized
                system to produce coordination. <a href="#fig5">Figure 5</a> shows the number of
                time steps necessary for the decentralized system to exceed the mean coordination of
                the centralized system. The decentralized system takes more time than the
                centralized system to create coordination among agents. Furthermore, the number of
                time steps necessary for the decentralized system to exceed the mean coordination of
                the centralized system increases with the number of agents in the system. This is
                not because more interactions are necessary to order agents as the number of agents
                increases (there are as many interactions per time step as number of agents in the
                system). The structure of interactions in the decentralized system is such that the
                number of interactions per agent necessary for the decentralized system to
                outperform the centralized system increases with the number of agents.</p>
            <figure>
                <asset>
                    <label>Figure 5.</label>
                    <image id="fig5">
                        <title>Time steps necessary for decentralized system to exceed the mean
                            coordination of the centralized system with ten percent probability of
                            communication error.</title>
                        <caption>
                            <p>Note: In the centralized system, each agent conveys its number to a
                                central-coordinator. The central-coordinator orders the agents on a
                                line segment. In the decentralized system, at each time step, pairs
                                of neighbouring agents are randomly selected. Within each pair,
                                agents share information about each other&#x2019;s numbers. If the
                                agent on the left reports a number greater than the agent on the
                                right, the agents swap positions, otherwise the agents remain in
                                their present positions. Agents make errors in communicating their
                                numbers, i.e. with some probability an agent conveys an incorrect
                                number. Coordination is the negative mean of the absolute value of
                                the differences between the numbers of agents and the numbers of
                                their respective locations. The sum of these differences is divided
                                by the total number of agents and multiplied by negative one to
                                measure coordination. Zero indicates perfect coordination, lower
                                values of C indicate lesser coordination.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <source height="1" width="1" media-type="application/postscript"
                            >http://www.microsimulation.org/IJM/fig5</source>
                    </image>
                </asset>
            </figure>
        </content>
    </section>
    <section id="s4">
        <title>Implications and empirical predictions</title>
        <content>
            <p>One may view real world economic structures like markets, firms, and governments as
                complex mixes of centralized and decentralized systems. Real world structures have a
                variety of other attributes, for instance markets have prices, firms have bureaus,
                and governments have parliaments. Despite their simplicity, the structures studied
                in this paper generate several implications and empirical predications about the
                world outside the window.</p>
            <p>First, as communication technology improves, <i>ceteris paribus</i>, the organization
                of economic activities will become more centralized. Better communication technology
                allows for more accurate communication of information. This is equivalent to a
                decrease in communication errors in our model and consequent improvement in the
                relative performance of the centralized system. Perhaps this explains the emergence
                of behemoths like Walmart (<a href="#bib8">Bowersox and Daugherty, 1995</a>). Never
                before has a single firm employed nearly one percent of the US labour force (<a
                    href="#bib5">Axtell, 2001</a>).</p>
            <p>Second, autocratic societies will have greater variability than democratic societies.
                Empirical evidence suggests that dictatorships and other autocratic societies
                exhibit greater variability than democratic societies (<a href="#bib2">Almeida and
                    Ferreira, 2002</a>; <a href="#bib9">Doucouliagos and Uluba&#x015F;o&#x011F;lu,
                    2008</a>). <a href="#bib24">Rodrik, 1999</a> explains the greater variability of
                autocratic societies, and consequent collapse of economic growth, with their weaker
                ability to cope with external shocks. He argues that democratic societies have
                better internal conflict management mechanisms and therefore do not amplify external
                shocks as much as autocratic societies. Our paper provides an alternate explanation.
                We believe autocratic societies are less robust to communication errors of
                constituent parts than democratic societies because autocratic societies use more
                centralized decision-making than democratic societies. The greater variability and
                consequent extreme events in autocratic societies emerge from the way autocratic
                societies use dispersed information. In contrast to Rodrik&#x2019;s model, our model
                predicts that autocratic societies will exhibit greater variance than democratic
                societies even in the absence of external shocks.</p>
            <p>Third, economic organization will vary with product type. Certain personal services
                like massages involve information that is difficult to convey to higher levels of
                management. Information about standardized products like toothbrushes can be
                conveyed more accurately. It is more difficult to tell one&#x2019;s manager what
                kind of massage a customer wants than to tell her what kind of toothbrush a customer
                wants. This is perhaps why one does not find massage parlours with thousands of
                employees. <a href="#bib28">Stein, 2002</a> presents evidence on how smaller banks
                provide relationship based small-business lending and larger banks provide services
                that involve easy to communicate information. Areas of economic activity where
                information is difficult to convey will be organized in a decentralized manner.</p>
            <p>Fourth, urgent matters will be coordinated through centralized systems. This may be
                why most cities have a single fire-department but many housing agencies. Time is
                more significant in firefighting than in matching houses with buyers. The superior
                speed of the centralized system also explains the tendency to substitute
                decentralized systems with centralized systems in periods of war (<a href="#bib20"
                    >Milward, 1979</a>), p. 99&#x2013;100). As Sun Tzu said what is of the greatest
                importance in war is extraordinary speed (<a href="#bib29">Tzu and Cleary,
                2009</a>).</p>
        </content>
    </section>
    <section id="s5">
        <title>Concluding remarks</title>
        <content>
            <p>In this paper, we studied alternate structures of communication and decision-making.
                The structure of relations between agents affects the performance of economic
                systems even when the structure does not influence incentives to communicate private
                information. Our insights shed light on the internal structure of corporations and
                the relations between government agencies. Our model answers some basic questions
                like why most cities have a single firm department but many housing agencies.</p>
            <p>We have omitted a variety of factors relevant to the performance of economic systems
                including the computational limitations of information processing agents. But
                perhaps the greatest of omissions is an analysis of the relation between
                decentralization and the price system. Most economists believe markets are more
                decentralized than firms and governments (<a href="#bib4">Axtell, 2003</a>). Markets
                involve the use of the price system. Why does the most common form of decentralized
                coordination nearly always use the price system? Our hypothesis is that the price
                system decreases the time necessary to create coordination but makes markets less
                robust to communication errors. The price system is akin to a global
                telecommunication system which allows agents in one part of the system to know
                    <i>something</i> about the plans of agents in other parts (<a href="#bib13"
                    >Hayek, 1945</a>). The price system decreases the time necessary for a
                decentralized system to produce coordination because prices tell agents more than
                what they learn from local interactions. With the price system fewer local
                interactions are necessary for coordination than without the price system. However,
                the price system also increases the dependence between the information communicated
                by different agents. The impact of communication errors are no longer limited to
                their local vicinity. With the price system, communication errors influence the
                plans of agents far away from the interactions in which the errors occur. An
                increase in the dependence of the information communicated by different agents
                decreases the robustness of markets to communication errors. The influence of the
                price system on the robustness of markets is intricately linked to the business
                cycle phenomena. Exploring the relation between decentralization, the price system,
                and their consequence on aggregate fluctuations is a fruitful area for future
                research.</p>
        </content>
    </section>

</body>
